[
  {
    "question": "Who was the Viceroy of India at the time of Gandhiji's Dandi march?",
    "choices": "a) Lord Irwin\nb)Lord Linlithgow\nc) Lord\nReading\nd)Lord Willingdon",
    "answer": "(a) Lord Irwin",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one among the following American newsmagazines was\nhighly sceptical of Gandhiji's Dandi march initially but within a\nweek completely changed its opinion and saluted\nhim\nas\na\nSaint and Statesman?",
    "choices": "a) Saturday Evening Post\nb)Readers Digest\nc) Time\nd) Life",
    "answer": "(c) Time",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding the British colonial rule in India, consider\nthe following statements:\n1. Mahatma Gandhi was instrumental in the abolition of the system of 'indentured labour'.\n2.In Lord Chelmsford's 'War Conference' , Mahatma Gandhi did not support the resolution on recruiting Indians for World War:\n3.Consequent upon the breaking of Salt Law by Indian\npeople, the Indian National Congress was declared illegal by\nthe colonial rulers.\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\n(a)\n1 and 2 only\n(b)\n1 and 3 only\n(c)\n2 and 3 only\n(d)\n1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "(a)\n1 and 2 only\n(b)\n1 and 3 only\n(c)\n2 and 3 only\n(d)\n1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "(b) 1 and 3 only",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements about the Gandhi-Irwin\nPact is NOT correct?\na) Gandhi wrote a letter seeking an interview with the Viceroy\nb) The Civil Disobedience movement was to be discontinued\nc) The imprisoned freedom fighters were to be released\nd)AII the lands that had been confiscated were to be returned\nto the original owner",
    "choices": "a) Gandhi wrote a letter seeking an interview with the Viceroy\nb) The Civil Disobedience movement was to be discontinued\nc) The imprisoned freedom fighters were to be released\nd)AII the lands that had been confiscated were to be returned\nto the original owner",
    "answer": "(d) All the lands that had been confiscated were to be\nreturned to the original owners",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)\nWith reference to Indian freedom struggle, which\none of the\nfollowing statements is not correct?\n(a)The Rowlatt Act aroused a wave of popular Indian on and\nled to the Jallianwala Bagh massacre:\n(b)Subhash Chandra Bose formed the Forward Bloc.\n(c)Bhagat Singh was one of the founders of Hindustan Republican Socialist Association.\n(d)\nIn 1931, the congress session at Karachi opposed Gandhi\nIrwin pact:",
    "choices": "(a)The Rowlatt Act aroused a wave of popular Indian on and\nled to the Jallianwala Bagh massacre:\n(b)Subhash Chandra Bose formed the Forward Bloc.\n(c)Bhagat Singh was one of the founders of Hindustan Republican Socialist Association.\n(d)\nIn 1931, the congress session at Karachi opposed Gandhi\nIrwin pact:",
    "answer": "(d) In 1931, the congress session at Karachi opposed\nGandhi Irwin pact",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which\none\nof the following is\nNOT correct about Mahatma\nGandhi's Dandi Yatra or Salt March?\na) It was the first national activity in which women participated in large numbers\nb)Gandhiji allowed the women's participation at the request\nof Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay\nc) The march was fully covered by the Western press\nd) The march began after the failure of the First Round Table\nConference",
    "choices": "a) It was the first national activity in which women participated in large numbers\nb)Gandhiji allowed the women's participation at the request\nof Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay\nc) The march was fully covered by the Western press\nd) The march began after the failure of the First Round Table\nConference",
    "answer": "(d)",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The march began after the failure of the First Round Table Conference At which Congress Session was the Working Committee authorised to launch a programme of Civil Disobedience?\n(a) Bombay\n(b) Lahore\n(c)Lucknow\n(d) Tripuri",
    "choices": "(a) Bombay\n(b) Lahore\n(c)Lucknow\n(d) Tripuri",
    "answer": "(b) Lahore",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which Viceroy had observed; \"It's a beautiful world if it wasn't\nfor Gandhi\n? \na) Lord Irwin\nb)Lord Wavell\nc) Lord Mountbatten\nd)Lord Willingdon",
    "choices": "a) Lord Irwin\nb)Lord Wavell\nc) Lord Mountbatten\nd)Lord Willingdon",
    "answer": "(d) Lord Willingdon",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one among the following was demanded by the AIl India\nDepressed Classes Leaders\nConference at Bombay in 1931?\na) Universal adult suffrage\nb)Separate electorates for untouchables\nc) Reserved seats for the minorities\nd)A unitary State in India",
    "choices": "a) Universal adult suffrage\nb)Separate electorates for untouchables\nc) Reserved seats for the minorities\nd)A unitary State in India",
    "answer": "(b) Separate electorates for untouchables",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following drafted the resolution on Fundamental Rights for the Karachi session of Congress in 1931?\n(a)\nDr B. R Ambedkar\n(b)\nJawaharlal Nehru\n(c)\nDr Rajendra Prasad\n(d)\nSardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
    "choices": "(a)\nDr B. R Ambedkar\n(b)\nJawaharlal Nehru\n(c)\nDr Rajendra Prasad\n(d)\nSardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
    "answer": "(b) Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements about the Gandhi-Irwin\nPact of 1931 is correct?\na) The Government would\nnot release those prisoners\nwho\nhad been non-violent:\nb) The Government would\nnot release those prisoners\nwho\nhad indulged in the peaceful picketing of liquor and foreign\ncloth shops:\nc) The Congress did not agree to the suspension of the Civil\nDisobedience Movement:\nd) The Congress agreed to take part in the Second Round Table\nConference.",
    "choices": "a) The Government would\nnot release those prisoners\nwho\nhad been non-violent:\nb) The Government would\nnot release those prisoners\nwho\nhad indulged in the peaceful picketing of liquor and foreign\ncloth shops:\nc) The Congress did not agree to the suspension of the Civil\nDisobedience Movement:\nd) The Congress agreed to take part in the Second Round Table\nConference.",
    "answer": "(d) The Congress agreed to take part in the Second\nRound Table Conference",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements about the Salt March:\n1. The Salt March\nwas deliberately ignored\nthe European\nmedia.\n2. The Salt March\nwas\nwidely covered by the\nAmerican and\nEuropean press.\n3.The Salt March\nwas the first nationalist activity in\nwhich\nwomen\nparticipated in large numbers.\n4. The Salt March impressed upon the British the urgent need\nto devolve more power to Indians:\nWhich of the statements given above are correct?\na) 1,2 and 4\nb)2,3 and 4\nc) 3 and 4 only\nd)2 and 3 only",
    "choices": "a) 1,2 and 4\nb)2,3 and 4\nc) 3 and 4 only\nd)2 and 3 only",
    "answer": "(b) 2, 3 and 4",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which among the following\nwas\nNOT the provision\nof the\nGandhi-Irwin pact?\na) Immediate\nrelease\nof\nall political  prisoners\nof the\nCivil\nDisobedience. Movement\nb)Clause 2 of the March 1931 pact defined 'reservations and\nsafe- guards to cover financial credit of India\nc) The return of confiscated land already sold to third parties\nd)Reservation of 18 per cent seats for Depressed classes",
    "choices": "a) Immediate\nrelease\nof\nall political  prisoners\nof the\nCivil\nDisobedience. Movement\nb)Clause 2 of the March 1931 pact defined 'reservations and\nsafe- guards to cover financial credit of India\nc) The return of confiscated land already sold to third parties\nd)Reservation of 18 per cent seats for Depressed classes",
    "answer": "(d) Reservation of 18 per cent seats for Depressed\nclasses",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which one of the following Sessions of the Indian National\nCongress\nwas\nthe\nresolution\non\nFundamental\nRights\nand\nEconomic Policy passed?\na) Tripuri Session\nb)Lahore Session\nc) Lucknow Session\nd) Karachi Session",
    "choices": "a) Tripuri Session\nb)Lahore Session\nc) Lucknow Session\nd) Karachi Session",
    "answer": "(d) Karachi Session",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Khudai Khidmatgar (Servants of the God) was organised by\na) Mahatma Gandhi\nb)Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan\nc) M: A. Jinnah\nd)M: M. Malaviya",
    "choices": "a) Mahatma Gandhi\nb)Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan\nc) M: A. Jinnah\nd)M: M. Malaviya",
    "answer": "(b) Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who of the\nfollowing organised a march on the Tanjore coast\nto break the Salt Law in April 1930?\n(a)\nV.O Chidambaram Pillai\n(b)\nC. Rajagopalachari\nK. Kamaraj\n(d)\nAnnie Besant",
    "choices": "(a)\nV.O Chidambaram Pillai\n(b)\nC. Rajagopalachari\nK. Kamaraj\n(d)\nAnnie Besant",
    "answer": "(b) C Rajagopalachari",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why did Mahatma Gandhi undertake the fast unto death in\n1932.\n(a)\nRound table conference failed to satisfy Indian political\naspirations\n(b)\nCongress\nand\nthe\nMuslim\nLeague\nhad\ndifferences\nof\nopinion\n(c)\nRamsay MacDonald announced the Communal Award\n(d)\nNone of the statements (a), (b) and (c) given above is\ncorrect in this context.",
    "choices": "(a)\nRound table conference failed to satisfy Indian political\naspirations\n(b)\nCongress\nand\nthe\nMuslim\nLeague\nhad\ndifferences\nof\nopinion\n(c)\nRamsay MacDonald announced the Communal Award\n(d)\nNone of the statements (a), (b) and (c) given above is\ncorrect in this context.",
    "answer": "(c) Ramsay",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "MacDonald announced\nthe\nCommunal\nAward\nConsider the following statements:\n1.In the first Round Table Conference, Dr Ambedkar demanded separate electorates for the depressed classes:\n2.In the Poona Pact, special provisions for representation of the depressed class people in the local bodies and civil services were made\n3. The Indian National Congress did not take part in the Third Round Table Conference,\nWhich of the statements given above are correct? Choose the\ncorrect answer from the following options:\n(a)\nIand 2\n(b)\n2 and 3\n(c)\n1and 3\n(d)\n1, 2 and 3",
    "choices": "(a)\nIand 2\n(b)\n2 and 3\n(c)\n1and 3\n(d)\n1, 2 and 3",
    "answer": "(c) 1 and 3",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "For the Karachi session of the Indian National Congress in 1931,\npresided over by Sardar Patel, who drafted the resolution on\nthe Fundamental Rights and Economics Programme?\n(a)\nMahatma Gandhi\n(b)\nPandit Jawaharlal Nehru\n(c)\nDr Rajendra Prasad\n(d)\nDr B. R. Ambedkar",
    "choices": "(a)\nMahatma Gandhi\n(b)\nPandit Jawaharlal Nehru\n(c)\nDr Rajendra Prasad\n(d)\nDr B. R. Ambedkar",
    "answer": "(b) Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following began with the Dandi March?\n(a)\nHome Rule Movement\n(b)\nNon-Cooperation Movement\n(c)\nCivil Disobedience Movement\n(d)\nQuit India Movement",
    "choices": "(a)\nHome Rule Movement\n(b)\nNon-Cooperation Movement\n(c)\nCivil Disobedience Movement\n(d)\nQuit India Movement",
    "answer": "(c) Civil Disobedience Movement",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who among the following socialist activists persuaded Gandhiji not to restrict the salt march protest to men alone?\na) Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay\nb)Sarojini Naidu\nc) Matangini Hazra\nd)Mithuben Petit",
    "choices": "a) Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay\nb)Sarojini Naidu\nc) Matangini Hazra\nd)Mithuben Petit",
    "answer": "(a) Kamaladevi Chattopadhyay",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about Mahatma Gandhi's\nanti-untouchability campaign is/are correct?\n1. The\nAll\nIndia Harijan\nSevak Sangh\nwas founded\nfor this\npurpose:\n2. The campaign\nwas to root out\nuntouchability, since it did\nnot enjoy the sanction of the Hindu shastras:\nSelect the correct answer using the code given below:\na) 1 only\nb)2 only\nc) Both 1 and 2\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "a) 1 only\nb)2 only\nc) Both 1 and 2\nd) Neither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. The discussions in the Third Round Table Conference eventually led to the passing ofthe Government of India Act of 1935.\n2. The Government of India Act of 1935 provided for the establishment of an all-India Federation to be based on the Union of the provinces of British India and the Princely States.\nWhich of the statement(s) given above is are correct? Choose\nthe correct answer from the following options:\n(a)\n1\nonly\n(b)\n2 only\n(c)\nBoth 1 and 2\n(d)\nNeither 1 nor 2",
    "choices": "(a)\n1\nonly\n(b)\n2 only\n(c)\nBoth 1 and 2\n(d)\nNeither 1 nor 2",
    "answer": "(c) Both 1 and 2",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following question consists of statements: Statement I and Statement IL: Examine these two statements  carefully and select the correct answer using the code below:\nCode:\na) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the\ncorrect explanation of Statement\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not\nthe correct explanation of Statement | \nC\nStatement\nis true, but Statement Il is false\nd)Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true.\nStatement  : Mahatma Gandhi went on a fast unto death against\nthe Communal Award announced by the British Government:\nStatement I: The Poona Pact resulted in a joint electorate with\nan enhanced number of seats reserved for Depressed Classes:",
    "choices": "a) Both statements are individually true, and Statement Il is the\ncorrect explanation of Statement\nb)Both statements are individually true, but Statement Il is not\nthe correct explanation of Statement | \nC\nStatement\nis true, but Statement Il is false\nd)Statement | is false, but Statement Il is true.",
    "answer": "(a)\nBoth\nstatements\nare\nindividually\ntrue,\nand\nStatement II is the correct explanation of Statement 1",
    "topic": "Civil Disobedience Movement (1930-34)"
  }
]